<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Anaphora of Jacob of Edessa - Sachau 196</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>prepared and edited by</resp>
               <name>Ephrem Aboud Ishac</name>
               <note type="project-number">Project P 36649</note>
               <note type="project-name">Identifying Scattered Puzzles of Syriac Liturgical Manuscripts and Fragments</note>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>
               <orgName><ref target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/de/">FWF Österreichischer Wissenschaftsfond</ref></orgName>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>IMAFO</publisher>
            <date>19.08.2024</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Available under the
                  Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Staatsbibliothek Berlin</repository>
                  <idno>Sachau 196</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc><p>Paper</p></supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history><p>Written in 1280</p></history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction" n="Introduction" xml:lang="en">
            <div type="introduction-subsection" n="Jacob of Edessa - Life and Work">
               <p>Two reports about the life of Jacob of Edessa are preserved: One in the <emph rend="italic">Chronicle </emph> of Michael the Syrian (1126–1199 CE; Chabot 1901, 471-472; Chabot 1910, 445-446.) and one in the <emph rend="italic">Church History </emph> of Barhebraeus (1225/26–1286 CE; Abbeloos / Lamy 1872, 289-294.), both of much later time.</p>
               <p>Jacob of Edessa (c. 633–708) was a prominent Syriac scholar and bishop, significantly contributing to Syriac orthography, biblical studies, and church liturgy. Born in 633 in ʿAin Daba in the Chora of Antioch, a region with a bilingual Greek and Syriac culture, he received his early education under Chorepiscopus Quryaqos and furthered his studies at the famous Miaphysite Monastery of Qenneshrin. Jacob likely studied under Severus Sabukht and became fluent in Greek, enabling him to revise the Syriac Old Testament based on the Greek Septuagint. After studying in Alexandria, he returned to Edessa, where he gained fame as 'the interpreter of the books' and was consecrated as bishop by Patriarch Athanasius of Balad. However, his tenure as bishop lasted only four years due to his strong stance on church canons and opposition to compromises, leading to his resignation. Jacob then dedicated himself to teaching and writing in monasteries, significantly influencing Syriac liturgy and ecclesiastical discipline. In his final years at the Great Monastery of Tal ʿAda (nearby Aleppo), he spent nine years revising the Syriac Bible and producing theological and liturgical texts. He passed away on June 5, 708, leaving a lasting legacy in the Syriac Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction-subsection" n="The Edition of A. Raes">
               <p rend="space-after">A. Raes gives a list of 30 manuscripts containing the anaphora of Jacob of Edessa. (Raes 1981, 47-48.) This list can be supplemented with the following witnesses:</p>
               <p rend="space-after">Syro-Malankara Catholic Church. Major Archdiocese of Trivandrum, Trivandrum, India 20; 19th-20th century, 360 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/533764"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Church of the Forty Martyrs, Mardin, Turkey 614; 19th century, 259 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/503783"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Church of the Forty Martyrs, Mardin, Turkey 616; 15th century (?), 266 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/503785"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Church of the Forty Martyrs, Mardin, Turkey 621; 18th century (?), 406 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/503790"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Church of the Forty Martyrs, Mardin, Turkey 622; 18th century (?), 440 pages. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/503791"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Church of the Forty Martyrs, Mardin, Turkey 632; 16th century (?), 247 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/503801"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute, Kottayam, India 26; 20th century, 300 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/539521"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Université Saint-Joseph. Bibliothèque orientale, Beirut, Lebanon 9; 19th century (?), 109 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/609062"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Private Collection of Fr. Sleeba, Ernakulam, India 23; 19th century (?), 298 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/539214"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey 85 8/4; 16th century, 211 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/122742"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey 158; 15th century, 172 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/122799"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey 8/11; 86; 18th-19th century, 299 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/123386"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey DIYR 00168; 17th century, 128 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/123402"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey DIYR 00251; 18th century, 139 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/124539"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey DIYR 00270; 20th century, 442 pages. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/124558"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Meryem Ana Kilisesi, Diyarbakir, Turkey 284; 20th century, 495 leaves. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/124571"/></p>
               <p rend="space-after">Dayro d-Mor Gabriel, Midyat, Turkey MGMT 00116; 16th-20th century, 355 pages. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/123013"/></p>
               <p>Dayro d-Mor Gabriel, Midyat, Turkey MGMT 00181; 18th century, 408 pages. Available via the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library: <ref target="https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/500675"/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction-subsection" n="The Author of the Anaphora">
               <p>Raes casts doubt on Jacob of Edessa's authorship of the anaphora attributed to him, citing the late date of the surviving manuscripts (13th century) as evidence. While this is a valid point, it overlooks the fragility of liturgical texts. Frequent use in rituals can lead to damage and loss, potentially explaining the absence of earlier copies. The lack of earlier manuscripts shouldn't automatically equate to a late composition date for the anaphora.</p>
               <p>More importantly, a closer examination reveals a different story. Stylistic and theological similarities exist between the disputed anaphora and Jacob of Edessa's established works, particularly his commentary on the liturgy. These shared elements, whether specific phrasing, prayer structures, or underlying theological concepts, suggest a potential connection between the author of the anaphora and Jacob’s school of thought. Even if direct authorship remains unclear, this connection strengthens the case for Jacob’s influence on the anaphora's composition.</p>
               <p>Therefore, while Raes' observation on the late manuscripts warrants attention, it should not be the sole factor in determining authorship. Further research is needed to explore the possibility of earlier, damaged, or lost manuscripts. Additionally, investigating historical records or references to the Anaphora in other sources could shed light on its origins.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the text of this Anaphora shares terminology and imagery with Jacob's translations, and reflects themes from his translated works that suggest the community's suffering. Eschatological elements emphasize hope for the faithful after persecution and a coming judgement. The focus on angelic praise aligns with broader liturgical themes. While the Anaphora's theology might be considered "ecumenical" within West Syriac traditions, the compiler could have used techniques similar to Jacob's to express suffering and encourage perseverance. Ultimately, the presentation highlights the complexities of authorship attribution and the potential historical context embedded within this Syriac Anaphora.</p>
               <p>In fact, Jacob lived during a period of significant Muslim influence in Syria. His writings, particularly his canons and responses to inquiries, offer a glimpse into the challenges faced by Christians under Islamic rule. Therefore, as Jacob of Edessa might have used his translation of the Testamentum Domini, a text emphasizing eschatological themes, to comfort his suffering community, so his focus on an afterlife and ultimate judgement could have provided solace amidst present hardships. This connection between the Anaphora's eschatology and the historical context adds another layer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction-subsection" n="The Present Edition">
               <p>The manuscript chosen, Berlin, Sachau 196, a collection of Syriac Anaphoras dated back to 1280 AD. Several aspects make Sachau 196 a valuable witness for studying the Jacob of Edessa’s Anaphora:</p>
               <p><emph rend="italic">Evidence of Active Use in Prayer</emph>:  Sachau 196 bears significant evidence of having been actively used in liturgical practices. The presence of wax marks throughout the manuscript, most likely caused by candles during prayer services, clearly demonstrates this. These wax marks are; they are physical proof that the text was not simply a theoretical document but a practical resource used in worship.</p>
               <p><emph rend="italic">Potential Reliability</emph>: Liturgical texts used in actual worship are more likely to have remained faithful to the original form compared to purely academic copies. Since Sachau 196 shows clear signs of active use through the presence of wax marks, it offers a potentially more reliable representation of the Anaphora as it was likely used historically.</p>
               <p><emph rend="italic">Relatively Early Date</emph>: While not the earliest surviving Syriac Anaphora manuscript (most pre-9th century examples are fragments), Sachau 196 is relatively old.</p>
               <p><emph rend="italic">Placement of the Anaphora</emph>:  The Anaphora of Jacob of Edessa is the first complete text in Sachau 196, followed by three others. This placement might suggest a level of prominence for our Anaphora within this particular collection.</p>
               <p><emph rend="italic">Official Note Regarding Another Anaphora</emph>: An interesting note by the Syriac Orthodox Patriarch Ignatius IV appears next to a different Anaphora in the manuscript, instructing clergy to pray using that specific text. This suggests a level of control by the Church hierarchy over which Anaphoras were used, but also highlights the diversity of liturgical texts in circulation during this period.</p>
               <p>Finally, while Sachau 196 may not be the definitive version of Jacob of Edessa’s Anaphora, its status as a liturgical text with physical evidence of use (wax marks), along with its unique features, makes it a valuable testimony for examining the content and potential historical context of this liturgy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction-subsection" n="The Significance of the Anaphora of Jacob of Edessa">
               <p>The Anaphora attributed to Jacob of Edessa holds significance for several reasons:</p> 
               <p>Firstly, it offers a glimpse into a specific historical context. The repeated emphasis on "true faith" alongside references to suffering suggests the Anaphora originated from a community facing persecution. This could be due to religious conflict or the rise of Islam. By studying this text, we gain insight into the challenges faced by Syriac Christians during that period.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Anaphora might be linked to Jacob of Edessa himself. If authorship is confirmed, it would shed light on Jacob's theological views and the conflicts he had with the Church hierarchy. His struggles to uphold Church canons might be reflected in the emphasis on "true faith."</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this Anaphora contributes to our understanding of Syriac liturgy. By adding to the known body of Syriac liturgical texts, it helps us comprehend the development and diversity of Syriac Eucharistic prayers.</p>
               <p>The peculiar features of this Anaphora also deserve attention. The repeated use of "true faith" suggests a community actively defining and defending its beliefs against external pressures or perceived unorthodoxy. The text might even allude to an internal conflict within the Church, with the author's community considering themselves the true believers. Interestingly, the Anaphora links suffering and persecution with maintaining true faith. This suggests an eschatological interpretation – enduring hardship demonstrates true faith and leads to future reward.</p>
               <p>However, situating this specific Anaphora within the broader liturgical and theological development is challenging due to the uncertainty surrounding its authorship and date. Nevertheless, some general observations can be made. This Anaphora contributes to the rich tradition of Syriac Eucharistic prayers, demonstrating the diversity within Syriac liturgical practices. The emphasis on "true faith" might reflect broader theological debates within the Syriac Orthodox Church during this period. The themes of persecution and endurance might resonate with other Syriac writings that addressed similar challenges faced by the Church.</p>
               <p>Further research is needed to definitively determine the authorship and historical context of the Anaphora. Examining other Syriac theological and liturgical texts from the same period (as hoped from building Syriac Liturgical Corpus) could provide valuable context and help situate this Anaphora within the broader historical and theological landscape.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="transcription" xml:lang="syc">
            <ab type="page" n="1r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Title" xml:id="sachau-196-1">
                  <pb n="1r"/>
               <lb n="1"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܬܘܒ ܐܢܢܐܦܘܪܐ ܕܩܕ̄[ܝܫܐ] ܡܪܝ ܝܥܩܘܒ</hi>
               <lb n="2"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܕܐܘܪܗܝ</hi></seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer before Peace" xml:id="sachau-196-2">ܩ܏ܕܡ<hi rend="emphasized">ܨܠܘܬܐ ܕܩܕܡ ܫܠܡܐ</hi> 
               <lb n="3"/><hi rend="emphasized">[ܟܗܢܐ]</hi>ܐܠܗܐ ܐܒܐ ܕܟܠ ܘܡܪܐ ܡܪ̈ܘܬܐ. ܗ̇ܘ
               <lb n="4"/>ܝܠܘܕܐ ܡܬܘܡܝܐ <note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">in marg.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">ܕܝܠܕ ܡܠܬܐ</foreign></note> ܡܬܘܡܝܐ ܘܠܐ ܙܒܢܐܝܬ ܘܠܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܡܬܦܫܩܢܐܝܬ. ܗ̇ܘ ܡܒܘܥܐ ܕܫܠܡܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܘܢܒܥܐ ܕܫܝܢܐ ܘܬܗܘܡܐ ܕܚܘܒܐ ܡܫܡܠܝܐ.
               <lb n="7"/>ܐܢܬ ܐܘ ܝ̇ܗܘܒܐ ܕܫܝܢܐ. ܐܫܘܐ ܠܟܠܢ
               <lb n="8"/>ܕܪܘܚܢܐܝܬ ܘܫܦܝܐܝܬ ܘܠܐ ܕܠܝܚܐܝܬ.
               <lb n="9"/>ܢܥܲܦܩ ܘܢܢܲܫܩ ܚܕ ܠܚܕ ܒܚܘ̣ܒܐ
               <lb n="10"/>ܫܪܝܪܐ ܕܡܥܠܝ ܡܢ ܢܟܝܠܘܬܐ: ܕܒܐܝܕ̈ܘ[ܗܝ]
               <lb n="11"/>ܕܝܠܗ ܕܡܫܲܟܢܢܐ ܕܫܝܢܐ ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ
               <lb n="12"/>ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ. ܕܥܡܗ ܠܟ ܦܐܐ ܏ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ]
               <lb n="13"/>ܘܐܝܩܪܐ ܘܐܘܚܕܢܐ ܥܡ ܪܘܚܐ ܕܝܠܟ.
               <lb n="14"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܢܬܠ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="First Benediction" xml:id="sachau-196-3"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܡܟܝܠ
               <lb n="15"/>ܕܐܬܡܲܙܓܢܢ ܘܐܬܚܲܝܕܢܢ ܚܕ ܠܚܕ
               <lb n="16"/>ܒܚܘܒܐ ܫܪܝܪܐ ܘܒܪܘܚܐ ܡܟܝܟܬܐ.
               <lb n="17"/>ܘܫܠܚܢܢ ܠܥܬܝܩܘܬ ܡ̈ܐܢܐ ܕܒܪܢܫܢ
               <lb n="18"/>ܥܬܝܩܐ. ܘܠܨܘܪ̈ܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܩܕܡ
               <lb n="19"/>ܡܪܚܡܢܘܬܟ ܐܪܟܢܢ. ܒܥܝܢܢ ܡܢ ܛܒܘܬܟ
               <lb n="20"/>ܟܝ̇ܢܝܬܐ. ܐܫ̣ܘܕ  ܥܠ ܟܠܗ̇ ܐܘܡܬܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="1v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="First Benediction" xml:id="sachau-196-4" prev="#sachau-196-3">
                  <pb n="1v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܘܝܪܬܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܒܕܡܐ ܦܪܘܩܝܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܕܡܫܝܚܟ ܐܙܕܒܢܬ݀. ܟܠܗܝܢ ܒܘܪ̈ܟܬܟ
               <lb n="3"/>ܫܦܝܥ̈ܬܐ. ܘܟܠܗܝܢ ܛܝܒ̈ܘܬܟ ܓܡܝܪ̈ܬܐ.
               <lb n="4"/>ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܒܠܫ̈ܢܐ ܕܡܚܲܝܕܝܢ ܒܚܕ ܓܘܫܡܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܩܕܝܫܐ ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ. ܘܒܐܝܕ̈ܘܗܝ
               <lb n="6"/>ܢܣܩ ܠܟ ܏ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ] ܘܬܘܕܝܬܐ ܘܠܪܘܚܐ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ].
               <lb n="7"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer over the Veil" xml:id="sachau-196-5"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܐܢܬ ܗܘ ܗ̇ܘ ܕܒܛܒܘܬ
               <lb n="8"/>ܛܘܒܬܢܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܕܝܠܟ ܟܝ̇ܢܝܬܐ ܘܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ
               <lb n="9"/>ܠـܚܘܕ ܕܐܘܣܝܐܝܬ ܥܙܝ̣ܠܝܢ ܒܟ. ܡܢ
               <lb n="10"/>ܠܐ ܡܕܡ ܡܢ ܒܪܝܫܝܬ ܠܢ ܒܪܝ̣ܬ
               <lb n="11"/>ܒܨܠܡܐ ܫܒܝ̣ܚܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܟ. ܘܟܕ
               <lb n="12"/>ܐܬܚܒܠܢܢ ܘܠܚܒ̇ܠܐ ܫܪܟܢܢ. ܘܒܗ̇
               <lb n="13"/>ܒܛܒܘܬܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܝܠܟ. ܘܠܘ ܒܙܕܝܩܘܬܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܕܝܠܢ. ܠܡܠܬܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="15"/>ܫܕܪܬ ܠܦܘܪܩܢܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܐܢܬ ܗܫܐ ܐܘ 
               <lb n="16"/>ܡܪܝܐ. ܒܗ̇ ܒܛܒܘܬܐ ܕܒܗ̇ ܒ̣ܪܝܬ ܠܢ
               <lb n="17"/>ܡܢ ܫܘܪܝܐ. ܘܒܗܘܢ ܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܟܝܢܝ̈ܐ
               <lb n="18"/>ܕܒܗܘܢ ܦܪܩ̣ܬ ܠܢ ܒܫܘܠܡܐ.
               <lb n="19"/>ܐܬܚ̇ܫܚ ܥܡܢ ܒܫܥܬܐ ܗܕܐ. ܕܠܐ ܟܕ
               <lb n="20"/>ܡܬܩܪܒܝܢܢ ܠܪ̈ܐܙܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ
               <lb n="21"/>ܢܒ̣ܗܬ ܒܚ̈ܛܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܐܠܐ ܒܗܘܢ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="2r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer over the Veil" xml:id="sachau-196-6" prev="#sachau-196-5">
                  <pb n="2r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܢܬܚ̇ܠܠ ܡܢ ܨ̈ܘܥܨܥܐ ܘܨܐܬܐ ܕܚܛܝ̣ܬܐ.<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ
               <lb n="2"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܢܩܘܡ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܚܘ̣ܒܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܘܥܡ</seg>
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Sanctus" xml:id="sachau-196-7">
               <lb n="3"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ ܟܕ ܓܗܝܢ</hi>ܢܫ̇ܘܐ ܘܛܒ ܙ̇ܕܩ
               <lb n="4"/>ܕܬܬܒܪܟ ܘܬܫܬܒܚ ܘܬܬܗ̇ܕܪ.
               <lb n="5"/>ܘܬܬܪܡܪܡ ܡܢܢ ܐܘ ܐܠܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܘܠܘ
               <lb n="6"/>ܒܠܚܘܕ ܡܢܢ. ܐܠܐ ܘܐܦ ܡܢ ܟܠܗܘܢ
               <lb n="7"/>ܚܝܠ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܒܫܡܝܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܘܬܠܐ ܩܠܗ</hi>ܡܢܟ
               <lb n="8"/>ܓܝܪ ܪܥܠܝܢ ܘܡܬܪܗܒܝܢ. ܘܠܓܐܝܘܬܟ
               <lb n="9"/>ܡܝ̇ܒܒܝܢ ܘܡܗܕܪܝܢ. ܐܠ̈ܦ ܐܠ̈ܦܝܢ
               <lb n="10"/>ܘܪ̈ܒܘ ܪ̈ܒܘܢ ܕܗ̈ܘܢܐ ܫܡܝ̈ܢܐ ܘܝܗ̈ܠܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܥ̈ܠܝܐ. ܐܘܣ̈ܝܐܣ ܦܫܝ̈ܛܬܐ ܘܠܐ ܡܪ̈ܟܒܬܐ
               <lb n="12"/>ܕܡ̣ܢ ܢܒܪܫܬܐ ܡܬܝܕܥܢܝܬܐ ܦܣܝ̈ܩܢ
               <lb n="14"/>ܠܟ ܡܒܪ̈ܟܢ. ܛܐܟܣ̈ܝܤ ܬܡܝ̈ܗܬܐ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܕܚ̈ܝܠܬܐ ܕܡܢ ܓܘܙܠܬܐ ܕܢܘܪܐ
               <lb n="16"/>ܩܠܝܠܬܐ ܥܒܝ̈ܕܢ ܠܟ ܡܩ̈ܠܣܢ. ܦܠ̈ܓܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܥܙܝ̈ܙܬܐ ܕܬܗܪܐ ܕܡܢ ܒܝܢܬ ܣܦ̈ܘܬܗܝܢ
               <lb n="18"/>ܓܘܡܪ̈ܐ ܪ̈ܗܝܒܬܐ ܢܬܪ̈ܢ ܠܟ ܡܫܒܚ̈ܢ.
               <lb n="19"/>ܣ̈ܝܥܬܐ ܡܬܝܚ̈ܬܐ ܘܬܩܝ̈ܦܬ ܙܘ̈ܥܐ
               <lb n="20"/>ܕܟܪ̈ܘܒܐ ܛܥܝ̈ܢܝ ܠܓܢܝ̣ܙܘܬܟ ܠܟ
               <lb n="21"/>ܡܪܡܪܡܝܢ. ܛܟ̈ܣܐ ܡܛܟ̈ܣܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="2v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Sanctus" xml:id="sachau-196-8" prev="#sachau-196-7">
                  <pb n="2v"/>
                  <lb n="1"/>ܕܣܪ̈ܦܐ ܫܬܝܬܝ̈ܝ ܓܦ̈ܐ ܬܠܝܬܝ̈ܝ
               <lb n="2"/>ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ ܠܟ ܡܩܕܫܝܢ. ܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܟܕ
               <lb n="3"/>ܠܦܪ̈ܨܘܦܐ ܕܓܘܙܠܬܐ ܒܓ̈ܦܐ ܕܓܘܙܠܬܐ
               <lb n="4"/>ܡܢ ܓܘܙܠܬܟ ܠܐ ܡܣܬܝܒܪܢܝܬܐ ܡܚܲܦܝܢ.
               <lb n="5"/>ܒܩܝܢ̈ܬܐ ܫܦ̈ܝܬܐ ܘܣ̈ܦܘܬܐ ܪ̈ܡܬ ܡܢ
               <lb n="6"/>ܥܠ̈ܡܐ. ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ ܬܠ̈ܝܬܝܐ ܒܒܪܬ ܩܠܐ
               <lb n="7"/>ܚܕܢܝܬܐ ܖ̈ܥܡܝܢ. ܘܡܝܒܒܝܢ ܘܡ̇ܙܥܩܝܢ
               <lb n="8"/>ܘܩ̇ܥܝܢ ܘܐܡܪܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܩܕܝܫ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer after Sanctus" xml:id="sachau-196-9"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>
               <lb n="9"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܕ ܓܗܝܢ</hi>ܩܕܝܫܐ ܐܝܬܝܟ ܘܢܒܥܐ ܕ܏ܩܕܝܫܘ[ܬܐ]
               <lb n="10"/>ܡܪܝܐ. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܟܕ ܫܪܥ̣ܢܢ ܘܠܥܦܪܐ ܢܦ̣ܠܢܢ.
               <lb n="11"/>ܠܗ̇ܘ ܟܝ̇ܢܐ ܕܡܢܗ ܐܬܒ̣ܪܝܢܢ. ܡܢ ܗ̇ܘ
               <lb n="12"/>ܪܘܡܐ ܕܒܛܒ̇ܘܬܐ ܠܚܘܕ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="13"/>ܪܡܪܡܬ ܠܢ. ܢܒܝ̈ܐ ܫܕܪܬ ܠܬܘܪܨܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܕܝܠܢ. ܘܟܕ ܠܐ ܐܬܡ̣ܨܝܘ ܚܲܝܠܐ ܕܦܘܪܩܢܐ:
               <lb n="15"/>ܡܠܬܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܒܪܟ ܫܕܪܬ ܠܥܘܕܪܢܢ
               <lb n="16"/>ܘܐܬܓܫܡ ܡܢ ܓܒܝ̣ܠܬܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܕܢܗ̣ܦܘܟ
               <lb n="17"/>ܢܓܒܠܝܗ̇ ܡ̣ܢ ܕܪܝܫ. ܘܟܠܡܕܡ ܕܦܐܐ
               <lb n="18"/>ܠܒܪܢܫܐ ܩܒ̣ܠ ܚܠܦܝܢ. ܘܕܦܐܐ ܠܐܠܗܐ
               <lb n="19"/>ܣܥ̣ܪ ܠܦܘܪܩܢܢ.</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Words of Institution" xml:id="sachau-196-10"><hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܐ ܩܠܗ</hi>ܟܕ ܕܝܢ
               <lb n="20"/>ܠܐܡܪܐ ܢܡܘܣܝܐ ܗ̇ܘ ܕܠܗ ܠܐܡ̣ܪܐ          
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="3r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Words of Institution" xml:id="sachau-196-11" prev="#sachau-196-10">
                  <pb n="3r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܫܡ̇ܝܢܐ ܡܛܦܣ ܗܘܐ. ܥܡ ܬܠ̈ܡܝܕܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܕܝܠܗ ܩܕܝܫ̈ܐ ܐܟ̣ܠ. ܘܨܒ̰ܐ ܕܡܢ ܐܡܪ̈ܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܘܓܕ̈ܝܐ ܘܕܒܚ̈ܐ ܦܓܖ̈ܢܝܐ ܢܪܡܪܡ
               <lb n="4"/>ܠܢ. ܘܠܡܥܠܝܘܬܐ ܕܕܒܚ̈ܐ ܫܡܝܢ̈ــܐ.
               <lb n="5"/>ܘܪ̈ܐܙܐ ܐܠܗ̈ܝܐ ܢܥܲܠܐ ܠܢ. ܒܗ̇ܘ ܪܡܫܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܕܥܬܝܕ ܗܘܐ ܕܢܬܠ ܗ̣ܘ ܠܗ ܕܒܚܐ
               <lb n="7"/>ܚܠܦܝܢ. ܠܚܡܐ ܢܣ̣ܒ ܒܐܝ̈ܕܝܐ ܕܝܠܗ
               <lb n="8"/>ܩܕܝܫ̈ܬܐ ܘܪ̈ܡܬ ܡܢ ܛܘܠܫܐ. ܘܟܕ ܬܠܐ
               <lb n="9"/>ܚܘܪܐ ܩܛܝܢܐ ܠܪܘܡܐ ܕܫܡܝܐ ܠܘܬ
               <lb n="10"/>ܐܒܐ. ܘܐܘܕ݊ܝ. ܒܲܪ݊ܟ. ܩܲܕ݊ܫ.
               <lb n="11"/>ܩ̣ܨܐ݉ ܘܐܟ̣ܠ ܘܝܗ̣ܒ ܠܬܠ̈ܡܝܕܐ ܕܝܠܗ
               <lb n="12"/>ܟܕ ܐܡ̇ܪ. ܕܣ̣ܒܘ ܐܟܘܠܘ ܡܢܗ.
               <lb n="13"/>ܗ̇ܢܘ ܦܓܪܝ ܕܚܠܦ ܚܝ̈ܐ ܕܒܖ̈ܝܬܐ.
               <lb n="14"/>ܡܬܩ̣ܨܐ݉ ܘܡܬܦ̇ܠܓ ܠܚܘܣܝܐ ܕܚܘܒ̈ܐ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܠܫܘܒܩܢܐ ܕܚ̈ܛܗܐ. ܘܠܚ̈ܝܐ ܕܠܥܠܡ
               <lb n="16"/>ܥܠܡܝܢ܀ ܗܟܢܐ ܬܘܒ ܡ̇ܙܓ ܡܡܙܓܐܝܬ
               <lb n="17"/>ܡܢ ܚܲܡܪܐ ܘܡܢ ܡܝ̈ܐ ܠܟܣܐ ܘܐܘܕܝ
               <lb n="18"/>ܥܠܘܗܝ. ܡܢ ܒܬܪ ܕܒܲܣܡ ܠ̈ܬܠܡ̣܏ܝܕܘ[ܗܝ]
               <lb n="19"/>ܒܦܬܘܪܐ ܕܪ̈ܐܙܐ. ܘܒܪ݊ܟ. ܩܲܕ݊ܫ.
               <lb n="20"/>ܘܐܘܫܛ ܠܫܠܝܚ̈ܐ ܘܐܡ̣ܪ. ܗ̇ܢܘ ܕܡܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="3v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Words of Institution" xml:id="sachau-196-12" prev="#sachau-196-11">
                  <pb n="3v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܕܝܠܝ. ܕܐܫ̇ܕ ܐܢܐ ܠܗ ܚܠܦ ܚ̈ܝܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܕܥܠܡܐ. ܘܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܡܗܝܡܢܝܢ ܡܙܡܢ
               <lb n="3"/>ܠܚ̈ܝܐ ܕܠܥܠܡ ܥܠܡܝܢ ܀ ܘܗܟܢܐ
               <lb n="4"/>ܥܒܕܘ. ܟܠ ܐܡܬܝ ܕܐܟܠܝܢ ܐܢܬܘܢ
               <lb n="5"/>ܦܓܪܐ ܗܢܐ ܘܫ̇ܬܝܢ ܐܢܬܘܢ ܟܣܐ ܗܢܐ.
               <lb n="6"/>ܐܬܥ̇ܗܕܘ ܠܡܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܝ ܥܕܡܐ
               <lb n="7"/>ܕܐܬܐ ܐܢ̣ܐ.<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܡܘܬܟ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Anamnesis" xml:id="sachau-196-13"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܘܟܕ
               <lb n="8"/>ܠܡܕܒܪܢܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܠܥܠ ܡ̣ܢ
               <lb n="9"/>ܟܝ̇ܢܐ: ܥܠ ܠܘܚ̈ܐ ܕܠܒܘ̈ܬܢ ܟܬܒܝܢܢ.
               <lb n="10"/>ܘܠܪ̈ܙܐ ܬܡܝ̈ܗܐ ܕܬܡ̈ܝܗܬܟ ܐܘ
               <lb n="11"/>ܡܠܬܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܒܥܝ̈ܢܐ ܕܬܪ̈ܥܝܬܢ
               <lb n="12"/>ܚ̇ܙܝܢܢ. ܘܐܦ ܠܕܢܚ̣ܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܙܝܥ̣ܐ
               <lb n="13"/>ܘܕܚܝ̣ܠܐ ܕܡܐܬܝܬܟ ܗ̇ܝ ܬܪܝܢܝܬܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܡܬܥ̇ܗܕܝܢܢ. ܐܡܬܝ ܕܐܝܟ ܒܪܩܐ
               <lb n="15"/>ܥܙܝܙܐ ܡܢ ܡܕܢܚܐ ܕܢ̇ܚ ܐܢܬ.
               <lb n="16"/>ܘܠܫܬܐܣ̈ܝܗ̇ ܕܡܬܥܡܪܢܝܬܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܒܚܲܝܠܐ ܕܥܙܝܙܘܬܟ ܡܲܪܥܠ ܐܢܬ.
               <lb n="18"/>ܐܡܬܝ ܕܥܠ ܥܢ̈ܢܝ ܫܡܝܐ ܒܙܘܚܐ
               <lb n="19"/>ܪܒܐ ܐܬܐ ܐܢܬ. ܘܥܠ ܬܪܘܢܘܣ ܓܐܝܐ
               <lb n="20"/>ܕܓܐܝܘܬܟ ܒܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܐ ܡܬܡܲܠܠܢܐܝܬ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="4r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Anamnesis" xml:id="sachau-196-14" prev="#sachau-196-13">
                  <pb n="4r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܝ̇ܬܒ ܐܢܬ. ܐܡܬܝ ܕܡܣܲܪܩܐ ܐܪܥܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܐܝܟ ܡܐܢܐ ܕܦܲܚܪܐ ܠܦܓܖ̈ܐ ܕܚܡܝ̣ܠܝܢ
               <lb n="3"/>ܒܗ̇. ܘܡܥܝ̣ܪܐ ܫܝܘܠ ܐܝܟ ܕܡܢ
               <lb n="4"/>ܫܢ̣ܬܐ ܠܥܢ̈ܝܕܐ ܕܫܟܝ̣ܒܝܢ ܒܗ̇. ܐܡܬܝ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܠܝܬ ܒܘܝܐܐ ܠܐܒ̣ܠܐ ܕܪ̈ܫܝܥܐ ܐܦܠܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܟܡܝܪܘܬܐ ܠܚܕܘܬܐ ܕܙܕܝܩ̈ܐ. ܒܗ̇ܝ
               <lb n="7"/>ܫܥܬܐ ܕܚܝ̣ܠܬܐ. ܬܟܪܐ ܠܡܪܚܡܢܘܬܟ
               <lb n="8"/>ܡܪܝܐ. ܥܠ ܥܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܘܝܪܬܘܬܟ.
               <lb n="9"/>ܠܐ ܬܦܣ̣ܘܩ ܣܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܡܢ
               <lb n="10"/>ܛܝܒܘܬܟ: ܘܠܐ ܬܓܠ̣ܘܙ ܬܘܟܠܢܐ ܕܝܠܢ
               <lb n="11"/>ܡܢ ܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܕܒܣܝܡܘܬܟ. ܠܐ
               <lb n="12"/>ܢܚܲܦܘܢ ܚ̈ܛܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܠܛܒܥܐ ܕܡܪܘܢ
               <lb n="13"/>ܕܝܠܟ ܗ̇ܘ ܩܕܝܫܐ. ܠܐ ܢܫܬܠܚ ܒܝܕ
               <lb n="14"/>ܣܟ̈ܠܘܬܢ ܡ̣ܢ ܡܥܡܘܕܝܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܗ̇ܝ
               <lb n="15"/>ܐܠܗܝܬܐ. ܠܐ ܬܗܘܐ ܠܘܬܢ ܕܠܐ
               <lb n="16"/>ܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܡܪܝܐ. ܘܠܐ ܬܗܦܟ ܐܦܝ̈ܟ
               <lb n="17"/>ܡܢܢ. ܠܐ ܢܒܥܐ ܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܘܠܝܬ
               <lb n="18"/>ܕܡܪܚܡ. ܠܐ ܢܒܟ̣ܐ ܒܚܫܐ ܘܠܝܬ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="4v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Anamnesis" xml:id="sachau-196-15" prev="#sachau-196-14" rend="empty-page">
                  <pb n="4v"/>
                  Blank page
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="5r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Anamnesis" xml:id="sachau-196-16" prev="#sachau-196-15">
                  <pb n="5r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܕܡܒܲܝܐܐ. ܠܐ ܢܫܬܢܲܩ ܒܓܗܢܐ ܘܠܝܬ
               <lb n="2"/>ܕܚ̇ܐܣ. ܠܐ ܢܬܕܓܠܘܢ ܠܘܬܢ ܫܘ̈ܘܕܝܟ
               <lb n="3"/>ܫܖ̈ܝܪܐ ܒܝܕ ܚܛܗ̈ܐ ܘܫܘܪ̈ܥܬܐ ܕܝܠܢ.
               <lb n="4"/>ܠܐ ܥܡ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܛܠܡ̣ܘ ܠܚ̈ܫܝܟ:
               <lb n="5"/>ܢܬܚܲܝܒܘܢ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܠܐ ܟܦ̣ܪܘ ܒܨܠܝܒܟ.
               <lb n="6"/>ܠܐ ܥܡ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܠܐ ܐܘ̇ܕܝ̣ܘ ܒܟ. ܢܬܡ̣ܢܘܢ
               <lb n="7"/>ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܗܝܡܢܘ ܒܟ. ܚܢܢ ܐܝ̇ܬܝܢ
               <lb n="8"/>ܡܪܝܐ. ܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܩܲܒܠܢܢ ܨܥܪܐ ܘܡܘܝܩܐ
               <lb n="9"/>ܚܠܦ ܫܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܩܕܝܫܐ. ܗ̇ܢܘܢ
               <lb n="10"/>ܕܐܬܩܲܦܚܢܢ ܡܢ ܥܡ̈ܡܐ ܢܘܟܪ̈ܝܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܚܠ̣ܦ ܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܫܪܝܪܬܐ. ܕܠܐ
               <lb n="12"/>ܟܦ̣ܪܢܢ ܒܟ ܠܐ ܬܟܦ̣ܘܪ ܒܢ. ܕܠܐ ܛܠܡܢܢ
               <lb n="13"/>ܠܡܘܟܟܟ ܠܐ ܢܬܛܠܡ ܡܢ ܒܘܣܡܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܕܥܡܟ. ܡܛܠ ܓܝܪ ܗܠܝܢ ܥܕܬܟ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܡܪܥܝܬܟ. ܡܬܟܲܫܦܐ ܠܟ ܘܒܐܝܕ̈ܝܟ
               <lb n="16"/>ܥܡܟ ܠܐܒܘܟ ܟܕ ܐܡ̇ܪܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܪܚܡ
               <lb n="17"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܐܦܚܢܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܠܟ ܡܫ̇ܒܚܝܢܢ
               <lb n="18"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܡܐ ܕܚܝ̣ܠܐ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Invocation of the Holy Spirit" xml:id="sachau-196-17"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ ܩܪܝܬܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ</hi>
               <lb n="19"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܟܕ ܓܗܝܢ</hi>ܐܝܢ ܐܠܗܐ ܪܚܡܥܠܝܢ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="5v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Invocation of the Holy Spirit" xml:id="sachau-196-18" prev="#sachau-196-17">
                  <pb n="5v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܘܫܕܪ ܛܝܒܘܬܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܩܕܝܫܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܗ̇ܘ ܡܲܥܒܕ ܚܝ̈ܐ. ܗ̇ܘ ܫ̇ܘܐ ܠܟ
               <lb n="3"/>ܒܐܘܣܝܐ. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܡܲܠܠ ܒܢܒ̈ܝܐ. ܗ̇ܘ
               <lb n="4"/>ܕܚܲܟܡ ܠܫܠܝܚ̈ܐ. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܠܲܒܒ ܠܣܗ̈ܕܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܗܘ ܢܐܓܢ ܥܠ ܪ̈ܐܙܐ ܗܠܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܥܢܝܢܝ
               <lb n="6"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܩܘܪܝܠܠܝܣܘܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܟܕ
               <lb n="7"/>ܡܲܐܓܢ ܢܥܒ̣ܕ ܠܠܚܡܐ ܡ̇ܢ ܗܢܐ.
               <lb n="8"/>ܦ݊ܓ݊ܪ݊ܐ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܐܡܝܢ</hi>
               <lb n="9"/>ܘܠܟܣܐ ܗܢܐ ܢܚ̇ܘܐ. ܕ݊ܡ݊ܐ݊ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ
               <lb n="10"/>ܐܠܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܐܡܝܢ</hi>ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܟܕ ܡܬܡܙܓܝܢ
               <lb n="11"/>ܘܡܬܚ̇ܝܕܝܢ ܒܢ̈ܦܫܬܐ ܘܦܓܪ̈ܐ ܕܝܠܢ.
               <lb n="12"/>ܢܗܘܘܢ ܠܢ ܠܚܘܣܝܐ ܘܠܐ ܠܩܘܛܪܓܐ.
               <lb n="13"/>ܘܠܕܘܟܝܐ ܘܠܐ ܠܚܘܝ̇ܒܐ. ܠܦܐܪܪܣܝܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܕܩܕܡ ܬܪܘܢܘܣ ܕܚܝ̣ܠܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܟ.
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܠܚܘܠܛܢܐ ܕܥܡ ܐܡܪ̈ܐ ܒܢ̈ܝ
               <lb n="16"/>ܝܡܝܢܟ. ܡܛܠ ܕܫܪܝܪܝܢ ܘܡܗ̇ܝܡܢܢ
               <lb n="17"/>ܫܘ̈ܘܕܝܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܐܒܐ ܘܒܪܐ ܘܪܘܚܐ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ]</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-19">
               <lb n="18"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܠܗܕܐ ܕܒܚܬܐ ܡܩܪܒܝܢܢ
               <lb n="19"/>ܠܟ ܚܠܦ ܟܠܗ̇ ܥܕܬܐ ܬܪܝܨܬ
               <lb n="20"/>ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ]. ܚܠܦ ܦܐܛܪ̈ܝܪܟܘ ܚܠܦ ܐܦܝ̈܏ܣܩـ[ܘܦܐ].
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="6r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-20" prev="#sachau-196-19">
                  <pb n="6r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܚܠܦ ܩܫܝ̈ܫܐ. ܚܠܦ ܡܫ̈܏ܡـ[ܫܢܐ]. ܚܠܦ
               <lb n="2"/>ܡܗ̈܏ܝܡـ[ܢܐ] ܫܪ̈ܝܪܐ. ܚܠܦ ܕܘܝܘܬܐ ܕܝܠܝ
               <lb n="3"/>ܡܠܐ ܣܢܝ̈ܬܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܐ ܩܠܗ</hi>ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܒܝܕ
               <lb n="4"/>ܗܠܝܢ: ܬܬܪܡܪܡ ܘܬܬܢܨܚ ܥܕܬܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܝܠܟ ܡܫ̇ܒܚܬܐ. ܗ̇ܝ ܕܦܲܬܝܬ ܝܪ̈ܝܥܬܗ̇
               <lb n="6"/>ܡܢ ܣܘܦ̈ܝܗ̇ ܠܣܘ̈ܦܝܗ̇ ܕܥ̇ܡܪܬܐ.
               <lb n="7"/>ܬܬܥܫܢ ܒܥܘܫܢܐ ܕܕܪܥܟ. ܘܬܬܓܢܒܪܝ
               <lb n="8"/>ܒܚܲܝܠܐ ܕܓܢܒܪܘܬܟ. ܘܬܣܩܝ ܠܟ
               <lb n="9"/>ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ]<hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܟܕ ܒܠܚܘܕ ܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ
               <lb n="10"/>ܕܝܠܟ ܠܩܘܪ̈ܒܢܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܡܢ ܐܝܕܝ̈ܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܕܝܠܝ ܚܛ̈ܝܬܐ ܡܩ̇ܒܠ ܐܢܬ. ܘܐܦ
               <lb n="12"/>ܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܪܓܓܝܢ ܕܢܩܪܒܘܢ ܘܠܝܬ
               <lb n="13"/>ܠܗܘܢ ܚܝܠܐ ܐܬܕܟܪ ܒܖ̈ܚܡܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܝܬܐ</hi>
               <lb n="14"/>ܘܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܒܗ܏ܝܡ[ܢܘܬܐ] ܫܪܝܪܬܐ ܪ̈ܝܫܝܬܐ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܩܘܪ̈ܒܢܐ ܘܡܘܗ̈ܒܬܐ ܠܥܕܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="16"/>ܩܕܝܫܬܐ ܦܪܫܝܢ. ܘܒܣܢܝܩܘܬܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܘܚܣܝܪܘܬܐ ܕܡܛܪ̈ܦܐ ܡܫܬܘܲܬܦܝܢ
               <lb n="18"/>ܒܥܕܢܐ ܗܢܐ ܕܕܒܚ̣ܬܐ ܐܬܕܟܪ. ܘܠܐ
               <lb n="19"/>ܡܢ ܬܚܢܢܬܐ ܘܓܥܬܐ ܕܥܝ̈ܝܩܝ ܠܒܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="6v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-21" prev="#sachau-196-20">
                  <pb n="6v"/>
                  <lb n="1"/>ܬܗ̇ܡܐ ܡܪܝܐ. ܡܛܠ ܕܛܘܒܬܢܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܘܚܲܝܘܣܬܢܐ ܘܪܚܡ ܐܢܫܐ ܐܝܬܝܟ. ܘܠܟ 
               <lb n="3"/>ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ] ܘܬܘܕܝܬܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܐܬܕܟܪ ܡܪܝܐ
               <lb n="4"/>ܘܠܡ̈ܠܟܐ ܡܗ̈܏ܝܡ[ܢܐ] ܕܡܥܕܪܝܢ ܠܥܕܬܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܝܠܟ ܩܕܝܫܬܐ. ܐܬܟܬܫ ܚܠܦܝܗܘܢ
               <lb n="6"/>ܘܕܘܢ ܕܝܢܗܘܢ ܥܡ ܒܥܠܕܒ̈ܒܝܗܘܢ
               <lb n="7"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܝܬܐ</hi>ܘܠܕܐܒ̈ܐ ܛܪ̈ܘܢܐ ܕܠܗܝܩܐܝܬ
               <lb n="8"/>ܚ̇ܪܩܝܢ ܫܢܝ̈ܗܘܢ ܥܠ ܥܪ̈ܒܐ ܕܓܙܪܟ
               <lb n="9"/>܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ]. ܐܘܒܕ ܘܒܲܕܪ ܠܣ̈ܝܦܐ ܨܗܝ̈ܝ
               <lb n="10"/>ܠܕܡܐ ܕܣܓ̈ܘܕܝܟ. ܒܬܩܝܦܘܬ ܥܘܫܢܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܕܕܪܥܟ ܐܩ̣ܗܐ ܘܬܒܲܪ. ܘܠܦܠܚܘܬܐ
               <lb n="12"/>ܐܝ̇ܕܐ ܕܡܬܟ̇ܬܫܐ ܚܠܦ ܒܢܝܢܐ ܕܥܕܬܗ
               <lb n="13"/>ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ. ܒܚܲܝܠܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="14"/>ܠܐ ܡܬܟܲܒܫܢܐ ܚܲܝܠ ܘܥܲܕܪ. ܡܛܠ ܕܒܝܬ
               <lb n="15"/>ܓܘܣܐ ܘܦܪܘܩܐ ܘܡܥܕܪܢܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܐܝܬܝܟ.
               <lb n="16"/>ܘܠܟ ܏ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ]<hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܘܟܕ ܠܥܘܗܕܢܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܛܒܐ ܠܢܒܝ̈ܐ ܘܡܒ̈ܕܩܢܐ  ܕܓܠܝ̈ܢܐ ܡܲܝܬܐ
               <lb n="18"/>ܐܢܬ. ܐܬܕܟܪ ܠܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ ܡܪܝܡ
               <lb n="19"/>ܘܠܫܠܝܚ̈ܐ ܘܣܗ̈ܕܐ ܘܡܘܕܝܢ̈ܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܘܬܠܐ ܩܠܗ</hi>
               <lb n="20"/>ܠܡܐܪ̈ܙܢܐ ܕܪ̈ܙܐ ܠܐ ܡܬܥ̈ܩܒܢܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="7r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-22" prev="#sachau-196-21">
                  <pb n="7r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܕܡܕܒܪܢܘܬܗ ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ.
               <lb n="2"/>ܚܙܝ̈ܐ ܕܓܢ̈ܝܙܬܐ ܘ ܡܒܕܩܢ̈ܐ ܕܥܬܝ̈ܕܬܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܒܡܠܬܐ ܦܫܝ̣ܛܬܐ ܠܚܟ̣ܡܬܐ
               <lb n="4"/>ܕܚܟ̈ܝܡܐ ܐܒܗ̣ܬܘ. ܘܒܡܚܝܠܘܬܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܦܓܖ̈ܐ ܘܠܟܘܪ̈ܣܘܬܐ ܕܡܠ̈ܟܐ ܥܫܝܢ̈ܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܐܪܥܠ̣ܘ. ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܐܫܠܡ̣ܘ ܨܘܪ̈ܝܗܘܢ
               <lb n="7"/>ܠܫܢܕ̈ܐ ܘܐܘܠܨ̈ܢܐ ܚܠܦ ܫܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="8"/>ܩܕܝܫܐ. ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܟܦ̣ܪܘ ܒܥܠܡܐ
               <lb n="9"/>ܘܖ̈ܓܝܓܬܗ ܘܪܗ̣ܛܘ ܒܬܪ ܦܘܩܕܢܗ
               <lb n="10"/>ܕܡܫܝܚܐ. ܕܒܝܕ ܒܥܘ̈ܬܗܘܢ ܡܪܝܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܚܲܝܠ ܠܢܦ̈ܫܬܢ ܒܫܪܪܟ. ܣܲܬܬ
               <lb n="12"/>ܠܒ̈ܘܬܢ ܒܗܝܡܢܘܬܟ. ܡܛܠ ܕܝ̇ܗܘܒܐ
               <lb n="13"/>ܘܡܫܟܢܢܐ ܕܛܒ̈ܬܐ ܐܝܬܝܟ. ܘܠܟ ܫܘܒܚܐ 
               <lb n="14"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܘܒܗܕܐ ܫܥܬܐ ܐܬܕܟܪ ܡܪܝܐ 
               <lb n="15"/>ܠܡ̈ܠܦܢܐ ܬܪ̈ܝܨܝ ܫܘ̣ܒܚܐ. ܝܕܝܥ̣ܐܝܬ
               <lb n="16"/>ܕܝܢ ܠܐܝܓܢܐܛܝܘܣ ܐܬܢܐܣܝܘܣ ܓܪ܏ܝܓܘܪ[ܝܘܣ]
               <lb n="17"/>ܘܫܪܟܐ ܕܢܩܦܘ ܠܥܩܒ̈ܬܗܘܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܝܬܐ</hi>
               <lb n="18"/>ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܒܨܡܚܐ ܕܬܐܘܠܘܓܝܐ
               <lb n="19"/>ܢܦܝܚ̣ܬ ܒܪܘܚܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܠܚܫܘܟܘܬܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="7v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-23" prev="#sachau-196-22">
                  <pb n="7v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܕܟܠܗܝܢ ܐܡ̈ܘܬܐ ܐܢܗܪܘ. ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ
               <lb n="2"/>ܕܡܬܚܘ ܛܘܢ̈ܒܝܗ̇ ܕܒܪܬ ܥܡܡ̈ܐ 
               <lb n="3"/>ܙܒܝܢܬ݀ ܒܕܡܐ ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ.
               <lb n="4"/>ܡܢ ܣ̈ܘܦܝܗ̇ <note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">in marg.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">ܠܣܘ̈ܦܗ̇</foreign></note> ܕܡ̇ܬܥܡܪܝܢܬܐ. ܠܗܢܘܢ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܒܣ̈ܝܦܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ ܦܲܣܩܘ ܠܗܕ̈ܡܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܡܝ̈ܬܐ ܡܢ ܓܘܫܡܗ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܕܡܫܝܚܟ.
               <lb n="7"/>ܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܒܝܕ ܨܠ̈ܘܬܗܘܢ ܡܩ̈ܒܠܬܐ
               <lb n="8"/>ܡܪܝܐ. ܘܐܦ ܠܢ ܫܪܪ ܒܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ
               <lb n="9"/>ܕܝܠܗܘܢ ܬܪܝܨܬܐ. ܕܥܡܗܘܢ ܢ̇ܣܩ
               <lb n="10"/>ܠܟ ܏ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ] ܘܬܘܕܝܬܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܓܗܢܬܐ</hi>ܘܠܥܢ̈ܝܕܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܡܗ̈܏ܝܡـ[ܢܐ] ܕܡܛܠܬܗܘܢ ܐܬܩܪܒܬ
               <lb n="12"/>ܕܒܚܬܐ ܗܕܐ ܐܬܕܟܪ ܡܪܝܐ. ܒܫܥܬܐ
               <lb n="13"/>ܗܕܐ. ܡܫܡܗܐܝܬ ܕܝܢ ܠܐܒܗ̈ܝܢ
               <lb n="14"/>ܘܠܐܚܝ̈ܢ ܕܦܓܪ ܘܕܪܘܚ<hi rend="emphasized">ܬܠܐ ܩܠܗ</hi>
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܥܠ ܣܒܪܐ ܫܪܝܪܐ ܘܬܘܟܠܢܐ
               <lb n="16"/>ܕܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ ܕܒܟ. ܡܢ ܥܠܡܐ ܗܢܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܕܥܩ̈ܬܐ ܫܲܢܝܘ. ܘܡܢ ܚܝ̈ܐ ܗܠܝܢ
               <lb n="18"/>ܕܬܐܢܚ̈ܬܐ ܚܙܩ̣ܘ. ܘܠܘܬܟ ܡܢܥܘ.
               <lb n="19"/>ܠܐܒܗ̈ܝܢ ܠܐܚܝ̈ܢ ܠܪ̈ܒܢܝܢ. ܐܬܥܗܕ.
               <lb n="20"/>ܐܬܕܟܪ. ܩܲܒܠ. ܐܢܝܚ. ܒܥܘܒ̈ܐ
               <lb n="21"/>ܐܒܪ̈ܗܡܝܐ. ܒܡ̈ܫܟܢܐ ܕܚܕ̈ܘܬܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="8r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" xml:id="sachau-196-24" prev="#sachau-196-23">
                  <pb n="8r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܒܡܛ̈ܐܠܐ ܢܗܝܪ̈ܬܐ. ܒܥܠܡܐ ܕܦܨܝܚ̈ܘܬܐ.
               <lb n="2"/>ܒܥܕܬܐ ܐܘܪܫܠܡܝܬܐ. ܐܝܟܐ ܕܠܐ ܐܝܬ ܐܬܪܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܠܥ̈ܩܬܐ ܐܦܠܐ ܐܘܪܚܐ ܠܟܡܝܪܘܬܐ.
               <lb n="4"/>ܒܪ̈ܚܡ̣ܝܟ ܢܬܚ̇ܣܘܢ ܘܬܚܝ̣ܬ ܟܢ̈ܦܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܕܚܢܢܟ ܢܣܬܬܪܘܢ. ܘܚ̈ܛܗܐ ܕܝܠܗܘܢ
               <lb n="6"/>ܠܐܢܬܕܟܪܘܢ. ܡܛܠ ܕܠܝܬ ܕܐܬܚܪܪ ܡܢ
               <lb n="7"/>ܨܘ̈ܥܨܥܐ ܕܥܠܡܐ ܗܢܐ. ܒܟܠܗܘܢ ܠܒܝ̈ܫܝ
               <lb n="8"/>ܒܣܪܐ ܕܗܘ̣ܘ ܥܠ ܐܪܥܐ. ܐܠܐ ܐܢ
               <lb n="9"/>ܦܪܘܩܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܝܫܘܥ ܡܫܝܚܐ ܝܚܝܕܝܐ
               <lb n="10"/>ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ: ܕܒܐܝ̈ܕܘܗܝ ܐܦܚܢܢ ܣܲܒܪܢܢ
               <lb n="11"/>ܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܠܡܫ̣ܟܚܘ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܢܝܚ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Concluding Intercessions" xml:id="sachau-196-25">
               <lb n="12"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܘܠܡ̈ܘܒܠܐ ܝܩܝܪ̈ܬܐ ܕܚܢܢ ܠܢ
               <lb n="13"/>ܐܬܬܓܪܢܢ. ܒܥܠܡܐ ܗܢܐ. ܐܢܝܚ ܡܢ
               <lb n="14"/>ܨܘܪ̈ܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܡܪܝܐ. ܘܠܚ̈ܛܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܕܝܠܗܘܢ ܚܲܣܐ. ܫܒ̣ܘܩ ܐܥܒ̣ܪ.
               <lb n="16"/>ܕܒܨܒܝܢܐ ܘܕܠܐ ܒܨܒܝܢܐ. ܕܒܝܕܥܬܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܘܕܠܐ ܒܝܕܥܬܐ. ܘܠܐ ܬܒܲܚܢ ܥܡܢ
               <lb n="18"/>ܚܬܝܬܐܝܬ. ܟܕ ܩܝ̇ܡܝܢܢ ܩܕܡ
               <lb n="19"/>ܟܘܪܣܝܐ ܙܝܥ̣ܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܟ. ܐܠܐ ܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="8v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Concluding Intercessions" xml:id="sachau-196-26" prev="#sachau-196-25">
                  <pb n="8v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܐܬܚ̇ܫܚ ܥܡܢ. ܘܠܐ ܢܚ̣ܕܘܢ
               <lb n="2"/>ܒܥܠܕܒܒ̈ܝܢ ܒܐܒܕܢܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܐܝܟܢܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܕܐܦ ܒܗܕܐ ܐܟܡܐ ܕܒܟܠܗܝܢ
               <lb n="4"/>ܢܫܬܒܚ ܘܢܬܩܠܣ ܫܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ.</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="The Second Benediction" xml:id="sachau-196-27">
               <lb n="5"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܝܟܢܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܢܗܘܘܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>
               <lb n="6"/>ܥܡ<hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܩܬܘܠܝܩܝ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܩ̇ܨܐ ܘܪܫ̇ܡ</seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="9r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Lord's Prayer" xml:id="sachau-196-28">
                  <pb n="9r"/>
               <lb n="1"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܨܠܘܬܐ ܕܐܒܘܢ ܕܒܫܡܝܐ</hi>ܐܝܬܝܐ ܡܬܘܡܝܐ
               <lb n="2"/>ܘܐܒܐ ܩܕܝܫܐ ܕܒܪܐ ܡܬܘܡܝܐ. ܓܐܝܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܘܠܐ ܡܬܦܲܚܡܢܐ: ܘܠܐ ܡܬܕܪܟܢܐ: ܘܠܐ
               <lb n="4"/>ܡܬܦܲܫܩܢܐ. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܝܠ̣ܕܬ ܡܬܘܡܐܝܬ
               <lb n="5"/>ܘܠܐ ܙܒܢܐܝܬ ܠܡܠܬܐ ܐܠܗܐ. ܘܒܚܪܬܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܕܝܘܡ̈ܬܐ ܘܕܙܒ̈ܢܐ: ܒܙܢܐ ܕܡܥܠܝ ܡܢ
               <lb n="7"/>ܡܠܬܐ: ܘܡܕܒܪܢܘܬܐ ܕܪܡܐ ܡܢ
               <lb n="8"/>ܦܘܫܩܐ. ܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܐܘܣ̈ܝܝܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="9"/>ܒܟ ܫܟܝ̣ܚܝܢ ܐܘܣܝܐܝܬ ܐܬܚܲܫܚܬ
               <lb n="10"/>ܥܡ  ܓܒܝ̣ܠܬܐ ܕܡܝ̈ܬܐ ܕܠܚܒܠܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܫܪܟܬ݀. ܘܠܗ ܠܡ̣ܠܬܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܒܪܐ.
               <lb n="12"/>ܦܪܘܩܢ ܝܫܘܥ ܡܫܝܚܐ: ܫܕܪܬ
               <lb n="13"/>ܠܥܘܕܪܢܗ̇. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܟܠܡܕܡ ܠܦܘܪܩܢܢ
               <lb n="14"/>ܫܲܡܠܝ. ܘܐܠܦ̣ ܠܢ ܕܢܨ̇ܠܐ ܘܢܩܲܪܒ
               <lb n="15"/>ܠܟ ܬܟܫܦ̈ܬܐ. ܐܢܬ ܡܪܝܐ ܐܫܘ̣ܐ
               <lb n="16"/>ܠܟܠܢ. ܕܒܣܦ̈ܘܬܐ ܠܐ ܡܛܘ̈ܫܬܐ.
               <lb n="17"/>ܘܒܪܬܚܐ ܕܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ ܫܪܝܪܬܐ.
               <lb n="18"/>ܘܒܦܐܪܪܝܣܝܐ ܕܠܒ̈ܢܝܐ ܦܐܝܐ. ܢ̇ܙܥܩ
               <lb n="19"/>ܠܘܬܟ ܒܚܕ ܦܘܡܐ ܘܢܨ̇ܠܐ ܘܢܐܡܪ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="9v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Lord's Prayer" xml:id="sachau-196-29" prev="#sachau-196-28">
                  <pb n="9v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܐܒܘܢ ܕܒܫܡܝܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܢܬܩܕܫ ܫܡܟ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer after the Lord's Prayer" xml:id="sachau-196-30">
               <lb n="2"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܐܝܢ ܐܘ ܐܒܐ ܡܪܚܡܢܐ. ܠܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܬܪܦܐ ܒܢ ܐܝܕ̈ܝܐ ܕܢܦܠ ܒܢܣ̈ܝܘܢܐ.
               <lb n="4"/>ܕܠܐ ܡܨܝܢܢ ܠܡܛܥܢ. ܐܠܐ ܐܝܟ ܐܒܐ
               <lb n="5"/>ܚܲܢܢܐ ܣܥ̣ܘܪ ܠܒܢ̈ܝܐ ܡܚ̈ܝܠܐ. ܠܐ
               <lb n="6"/>ܬܓܠ̣ܘܙ ܠܢ ܡܢ ܛܝܒܘܬܟ. ܠܐ ܬܟ̣ܠܐ
               <lb n="7"/>ܡܢܢ ܪܕܝܐ ܕܒܣܝܡܘܬܟ. ܠܐ ܬܗܦܟ
               <lb n="8"/>ܡܢܢ ܦܪܨܘܦܟ. ܘܠܐ ܬܫܕܐ ܠܢ ܡܢ
               <lb n="9"/>ܛܝܪܟ. ܡܛܠ ܕܕܝܠܟ ܗܝ ܓܐܝܘܬܐ
               <lb n="10"/>ܘܬܫܒܘܚܬܐ. ܘܡܠܟܘܬܐ ܘܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ
               <lb n="11"/>ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ. ܕܒܐܝ̈ܕܘܗܝ ܘܥܡܗ
               <lb n="12"/>ܠܟ ܦܐܐ ܫ̣ܘܒܚܐ ܘܐܝܩܪܐ ܘܐܘܚܕܢܐ
               <lb n="13"/>ܥܡ ܪܘܚܐ ܕܝܠܟ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>
               <lb n="14"/>ܠܡܪܝܐ ܖ̈ܝܫܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܩܕܡܝܟ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="The Third Benediction" xml:id="sachau-196-31"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܠܥܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܡܪܝܐ ܗܢܐ ܕܥܡ
               <lb n="16"/>ܡܟܝܟܘܬܐ ܬܪܥܝܬܐ ܠܨܘܪܗ ܟ̇ܐܦ
               <lb n="17"/>ܩܕܡ ܪ̈ܚܡ̣ܝܟ. ܘܡܣܲܟܐ ܠܡ̇ܘܗ̈ܒܬܟ
               <lb n="18"/>ܫܦ̈ܝܥܬܐ. ܒܲܪܟ ܒܝܡܝܢܟ ܛܥܝ̣ܢܬ݀
               <lb n="19"/>ܒܘܪ̈ܟܬܐ. ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܟܕ ܡܢ ܟܠ ܛܘܠܫܐ
               <lb n="20"/>ܘܡܘܡ̈ܐ ܕܚܛܝܬܐ ܡܬܡܪܩܝܢܢ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="10r">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="The Third Benediction" xml:id="sachau-196-32" prev="#sachau-196-31">
                  <pb n="10r"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܘܒܦܓܪܐ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܘܕܡܐ ܐܠܗܝܐ ܕܡܫܝܚܟ
               <lb n="2"/>ܡܫܬܘܬܦܝܢܢ. ܟܠ ܩܘܠ̈ܣܐ ܘܪ̈ܘܡܪܡܐ
               <lb n="3"/>ܘܬܫܒܚ̈ܬܐ ܦܐܝ̈ܬܐ ܠܥܘܬܪܐ ܕܚܢܢܟ
               <lb n="4"/>ܡܣܩܝܢܢ ܘܠܝܚܝܕܝܐ ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ
               <lb n="5"/>ܘܠܪܘܚܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܗܫܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Prayer of Thanksgiving" xml:id="sachau-196-33">
               <lb n="6"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܫܠܡܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܥܡ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܬܗܘܐ
               <lb n="7"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܥܡ<hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܒܕܚܠܬܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>
               <lb n="8"/>ܩܘܕܫ̈ܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܚܕ ܐܒܐ<hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܚܕ ܐܒܐ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ]
               <lb n="9"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ ܨܠܘܬܐ ܕܒܬܪ ܢܣܝܒܘܬܐ</hi>
               <lb n="10"/>ܩܘܒܠܛܝܒܘܬܐ ܡܬܬܚܝ̣ܒܢܝܬܐ ܠܟ
               <lb n="11"/>ܐܠܗܐ ܡܩܲܪܒܝܢܢ. ܘܐܡܝܢܐܝܬ ܐܝܟ
               <lb n="12"/>ܕܡܲܨܝܐ ܡܲܘܕܝܢܢ. ܟܕ ܫ̇ܐܠܝܢܢ ܡܢܟ
               <lb n="13"/>ܐܘ ܐܠܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܕܪ̈ܙܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܩܕܝܫ̈ܐ
               <lb n="14"/>ܕܢܣ̣ܒܢܢ. ܠܚܘܣܝܐ ܕܚ̈ܘܒܐ
               <lb n="15"/>ܘܠܫܘܒܩܢܐ ܕܚ̈ܛܗܐ ܢܗܘܘܢ ܠܢ. ܒܛ܏ܝܒܘ[ܬܐ]
               <lb n="16"/>ܘܒܪ̈ܚܡܐ ܘܪܚܡ̣ܬ݀ ܐܢܫܘܬܐ ܕܝܚܝܕܝܐ
               <lb n="17"/>ܒܪܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܡܲܐܚܝܢܢ. ܥܡ ܪܘܚܐ
               <lb n="18"/>ܕܝܠܟ ܏ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] ܡܢܛܪܢܢ ܘܡܫܘܙܒܢܢ ܗܫܐ
               <lb n="19"/><hi rend="emphasized">ܥܡܐ</hi>ܐܡܝܢ<hi rend="emphasized">ܡܫܡ</hi>ܠܡܪܝܐ</seg><seg type="liturgical-section" n="Concluding Prayer" xml:id="sachau-196-34"><hi rend="emphasized">ܟܗܢܐ</hi>ܩܕܡܝܟ
               <lb n="20"/>ܡܪܝܐ ܡܪܚܡܢܐ. ܪܟܝܢܝܢ ܨܘܪ̈ܐ
               </seg>
            </ab>
            <ab type="page" n="10v">
               <seg type="liturgical-section" n="Concluding Prayer" xml:id="sachau-196-35" prev="#sachau-196-34">
                  <pb n="10v"/>
               <lb n="1"/>ܕܥܡܐ ܕܝܠܟ ܡܗ܏ܝܡ[ܢܐ]. ܫܟܢ ܠܗܘܢ 
               <lb n="2"/>ܐܘ ܒܣܝܡܐ. ܐܘܝܘܬ ܚܘܒ̣ܐ ܫܪܝܪܐ ܘܝܐܝܘܬ 
               <lb n="3"/>ܩܘܡܐ. ܟܕ ܡܲܫܦܥ ܐܢܬ ܥܠܝܗܘܢ
               <lb n="4"/>ܒܪ̈ܚܡܝܟ ܟܠܗܝܢ ܛܒ̈ܬܐ ܫܦܝܥ̈ܬܐ 
               <lb n="5"/>ܘܒܘܪ̈ܟܬܐ ܠܐ ܡܘ̈ܦܝܢܝܬܐ. ܘܢܲܛܪ ܐܢܘܢ
               <lb n="6"/>ܡܢ ܟܠܗܝܢ ܡܥܝ̈ܩܢܝܬܐ.<note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">in marg.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">܀ܘܣܬܪ ܐܢܘܢ ܡܢ ܟܠܗܝܢ ܡܣܓܦ̈ܢܝܬܐ ܘܐܫܘܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܕܢܫܡܥܘܢ ܟܠܗܝܢ ܝܡܝ̈ܢܝܬܐ. ܘܡܲܢܥ ܠܟܠܢ ܠܚܪܬܐ ܛܒܬܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܡܠܝܟܐ ܠܟܠܗܘܢ ܟ̈ܐܢܐ ܘܙܕܝ̈ܩܐ ܘܥ̇ܒ̈ܕܝ ܨܒܝܢܟ܀ ܐܢܬ ܓܝܪ</foreign></note>
               <lb n="7"/>ܐܝܬܝܟ ܒܠܚܘܕܝܟ: ܪܥܝܐ <note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">sup. l.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">ܘܛܒܐ</foreign></note> ܘܚܝܘܣܬܢܐ
               <lb n="8"/>ܕܐܫܠܡ ܢܦܫܗ ܘܦܲܨܝ ܢܦܫ̈ܬܐ ܐܒܝܕ̈ܬܐ.
               <lb n="9"/>ܘܠܟ ܏ܫܘ[ܒܚܐ] ܡܣܩܝܢܢ ܘܠܐܒܘܟ <note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">sub. l.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">ܗ̇ܘ ܡܦܢܝܢܐ ܕܫ̈ܐܠܬܐ ܛܒ̈ܬܐ</foreign></note> ܘܠܪܘܚܟ
               <lb n="10"/>ܩܕ[ܝܫܐ] <note type="textcritical-note"><foreign xml:lang="la">sub. l.</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="syc">ܘܡܲܐܚܝܢܐ ܕܒܪ̈ܝܬܐ.</foreign></note> ܗܫܐ.
               <lb n="11"/>[ܫܠܡܬ]
               </seg>
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" n="Translation" xml:lang="en">
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Title" corresp="#sachau-196-1">
               <p>Anaphora of the holy Mor Jacob of Edessa.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer before Peace" corresp="#sachau-196-2">
               <p>Firstly: Prayer before peace. Priest: God, father of all and lord of lordship, who is eternal begetter, who begets the eternal son eternally beyond time and mystically. Source of peace, fountain of tranquility and depth of perfect love.</p>
               <p>You are the giver of tranquility, make us worthy to embrace and kiss one another spiritually, with true love, without deceit, through your only begotten son, the giver of peace. With him befits you honor and power with your spirit.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
               <p>Deacon: Let us give.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="First Benediction" corresp="#sachau-196-3">
               <p>Priest: Now therefore, we are mingled and united with one another with true love and with humble spirit. We have taken off the garments of our old man and our necks before your mercy we incline. Therefore, we beseech your genuine grace: to be upon your entire nation and inheritance, which has been bought by the saving blood of your Christ, all sorts of your abundant blessings and your perfect graces, so that with tongues that have been united in the holy body of your only begotten son, through him may we offer up glory and thanks to you and to the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer over the Veil" corresp="#sachau-196-5">
               <p>Priest: You are with your graceful benevolence and by the mercies that are essentially united in you, in the beginning, out of nothingness, you have created us in the glorious image of your greatness.</p>
               <p>When we became corrupted and were reduced to destruction, by your grace and not because of our righteousness, you did send God the word, your son, for our salvation.</p>
               <p>Now, O Lord, by the same grace with which you have created us in the beginning and by the natural mercies with which you have redeemed us in the end, treat us now, lest we may be ashamed by our sins when we offer these holy mysteries. Rather, by them may we be cleansed from defilement and impurity of sin and offer up glory.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
               <p>Deacon: Let us stand.</p>
               <p>Priest: Love of ...</p>
               <p>People: And with ...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Sanctus" corresp="#sachau-196-8">
               <p>Priest inclined: It is meet and very right that you should be blessed, glorified, honored and extolled our God, not only by us, but also by all the heavenly hosts.</p>
               <p>With raised voice: Before you, they are trembling and terrified and as they make a joyful voice, glorifying your magnificence, the thousands of thousands and myriads of myriads heavenly intelligences and supernatural cohorts, simple and uncompounded substances, from immaterial flame are blessing you. Amazing and terrible orders made from the flames of swift running fire praise you.</p>
               <p>The mighty troops of awe, whose lips drop burning coals, praise you. The extended bands, with mighty movements, of the Cherubim who bear your invisible nature extol you.</p>
               <p>The orderly ranks of the six-winged Seraphim sanctify you with their thrice-holy hymns, as they cover their fiery faces with fiery wings from your intense flame. With pure melodies exalted above the world, with one voice, they clamor, shout, cry out.</p>
               <p>People: Holy ...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer after Sanctus" corresp="#sachau-196-9">
               <p>Priest inclined: O Lord, you are holy and the fount of holiness. When we have erred and fell into the dust, that nature from which we were created, by the exalted grace proper to you, you lifted us up. You sent the prophets for our direction and when they were unable to redeem us, you sent your son, the word of God for our help. He became embodied from our creation, in order to recreate it, and for us he received everything appropriate to a human being, but what is proper to God, he accomplished for our salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Words of Institution" corresp="#sachau-196-10">
               <p>With raised voice: As the lamb of the law typified the heavenly lamb, he ate it with his holy disciples wanting to lift us up from the lambs, kids and the bodily sacrifices, and to raise us to the loftiness of the heavenly sacrifices and the divine mysteries. On that evening in which he was about to give himself as a sacrifice for us, he took bread in his holy and undefiled hands, lifted his subtle gaze above to heaven, to the father and gave thanks, and he blessed, sanctified, broke, ate and gave to the disciples, saying: Take, eat from it. This is my body, which is for the life of the creation broken and divided for the remission of sins and the life eternal. Similarly, again he mixed water with wine proportionately in the cup and gave thanks over it. After having gladdened his disciples at the table of the mysteries he blessed, sanctified and stretched out to his holy apostle, saying: This is my blood which I shed for the life of the world and which invites those who believe in me, to the life eternal. Do thus, whenever you eat this body and drink this cup. Remember my death until I come.</p>
               <p>People: Your death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Anamnesis" corresp="#sachau-196-13">
               <p>Priest: And as we write upon the tablet of our hearts your dispensation which is above nature, and behold with the eyes of our minds the awe-inspiring mysteries of your wonderful deeds, O God the word we also remember your dreadful and awe-inspiring manifestation in your second coming, when you will shine out from the east as vehement lightening and shake the foundations of the earth with the power of your might. When you come amid great magnificence and sit on the glorious throne of your magnificience amid unspeakable glory, when the earth empties out like the potter's vessel the bodies that are hidden in it and Sheol awkakens from sleep the dead who lie down in it, then there will be no consolation for the lamentation of the wicked, and no sorrow for the joy of the righteous, at that dreadful hour, may your mercy have pity on your people and inheritance. Do not cut off our hope from your grace. Do not deprive our trust of your benevolence.
 May our sins not cover the seal of your holy myron. As a result of our sins, may we not be stripped off from your divine baptism. Do not treat us without mercy, Lord. Do not turn your face from us. May we not beseech mercy, having nobody to pity on us. May we not cry out in suffering, having nobody to console us.
 May we not be tormented in hell having nobody to show compassion. May not your true promises be withheld from us on account of our sins and transgressions. May those who did not deny your cross, not be found guilty with those who forsook your sufferings and passions.
 May those who believed in you, not be counted with those who did not confess you. O Lord, we have suffered insult and mocking for the sake of your holy name and we have been buffeted by the foreign peoples for your true faith.</p>
               <p>I think that the translation has an error here because the text is doubled. To be translated: dl' kprnn ... kd 'mr' (p. 5r)</p>
               <p>People: Have mercy.</p>
               <p>Priest: So we are ...</p>
               <p>People: To you we glorify.</p>
               <p>Deacon: How fearful is ...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Invocation of the Holy Spirit" corresp="#sachau-196-17">
               <p>Priest. Invocation of the Holy Spirit while being inclined: Indeed, O God, have mercy upon us and send the grace of your Holy Spirit, who is the giver of life, who is consubstantial to you, who spoke through the prophets, who made the apostles wise and who encouraged the martyrs, may he tabernacle upon these mysteries.</p>
               <p>Priest: Answer me.</p>
               <p>People: Lord have mercy.</p>
               <p>Priest: So that by tabernacling, may he make his bread the body of Christ our God. Amen. And may he manifest this cup to be the blood of Christ our God. Amen. When they are mingled and united with our souls and body, may they be for our absolution and not for indictment; for the purification and not for condemnation; for the confidence before the dreadful throne of your greatness and for the mingling with the lambs of your right hand side. For your promises are true and trustworthy, O Father, Son and the Holy Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Intercession Prayers" corresp="#sachau-196-19">
               <p>Inclined: We offer you this sacrifice for the entire Orthodox Church, for the patriarchs, bishops, priests, deacons, true believers and for my wretchedness which is full of hateful things.</p>
               <p>With raised voice: So that through these mysteries may your glorious Church be exalted and triumphant, whose tents you have broadened from one end of the world to the other. May she be strengthened by the might of your arm. Make her mighty by your heroism and may she offer up praise.</p>
               <p>Inclined: By your mercy, you alone accept these offerings from my sinful hands. Remember also all those who desired to offer but could not.</p>
               <p>Proclamation: O Lord, remember at the time of this offering, those who, with true faith, set apart the first fruits, offerings and gifts for the holy Church and participated in the need and poverty of those who are in tribulation. O Lord, do not disregard the supplication and imploring of those who are distressed in heart, for you are gracious, benevolent and the lover of mankind. To you is the glory and thanksgiving.</p>
               <p>Inclination: Remember, O Lord, the believing kings who assist your holy Church. Fight for them and pronounce judgment against their enemies.</p>
               <p>Proclamation: Annihilate and disperse the ravening wolves that are greedily gnashing their teeth against the sheeps of your holy sheepfold. By the intense might of your arm, make blunt and shatter the swords thirsting for the blood of your worshippers. Strengthen, O Lord, and help by your invincible strength the army that fights for the edification of the Church of your only begotten son, because you are the shelter, saviour and our help. To you is the glory.</p>
               <p>Inclination: O Lord, as you make good remembrance of the prophets and those who have declared your revelations, remember Mary, the mother of God, the apostles and martyrs and confessors.</p>
               <p>With raised voice: The divine teachers of the inscrutable mysteries of the dispensation of your only begotten, the onlookers of the hidden, the prophets of the events to come, who by simple word, have put to shame the wisdom of the wise, and in weakness of body have shaken the thrones of the mighty kings and have given their necks to torments and afflictions for your holy name, who have renounced the world and its desires and have run after the commandments of your Christ, o Lord, by their supplications, strengthen our souls in your truth, make firm our hearts in your faith, for you are the giver of good gifts. We offer up glory.</p>
               <p>Inclination: At this hour, remember, O Lord, the Orthodox teachers, namely Ignatius, Athanasius, Gregorius and those who follow their footsteps.</p>
               <p>Proclamation: O Lord, those who, by the brilliancy of theology, inspired by your Holy Spirit have illumined the darkness of every nation, who have extended the cords of the daughter of gentiles, bought by the blood of your only begotten son, from one end of the world to the other, why by the swords of the spirit have cut away the dead limbs from the holy body of your Christ. By their acceptable prayers, make us, O Lord, firm in their Orthodox faith, so that with them we may offer up praise and thanksgiving.</p>
               <p>Inclination: Remember, O Lord, at this hour the faithful departed for whom this sacrifice has been offered, especially our spiritual and temporal fathers and brethren.</p>
               <p>With raised voice: Those who, with true hope and trust in faith in you, have departed from this world of sadness and left this life of groans and have reached you, our fathers, brethren and teachers. Remember, receive and give rest in Abraham's bosom in the tents of joy, in the tents of light in the world of cheerfulness, in the Church of Jerusalem where there is no place for sorrow, or the way of sadness. Let them be avsolved by your mercy and may they be sheltered under the wings of your compassion. May their sins be not remembered, for there is no one among those who have clothed in the flesh on earth free from the world's defilements, except our Lord Jesus Christ, your only begotten son, through whom, we also hope to find mercy.</p>
               <p>People: Give rest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Concluding Intercessions" corresp="#sachau-196-25">
               <p>Priest: Relieve us from our necks, O Lord, the heavy burdens that we engaged in this world, and absolve; forgive and remove our and their sins, willingly or unwillingly, with or without knowledge. Do not examine us minutely, when we stand before the fearful throne of your greatness; look and treat us with mercy. May our enemies not rejoice in our ruin, so that in this and in all things your most honoured and praised name may be glorified and praised with that of our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="The Second Benediction" corresp="#sachau-196-27">
               <p>People: As it was.</p>
               <p>Priest: May ...</p>
               <p>People: With ...</p>
               <p>Deacon: Qatuliqi.</p>
               <p>Priest: Breaking (the bread).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer before the Lord's Prayer" corresp="#sachau-196-28">
               <p>Prayer of our father. Ethernal principle, holy father of the eternal son, hidden and inscrutable, glorious, incomparable, incomprehensible and ineffable, who brought forth God the word without beginning and time, and in the end of days and times in a manner beyond word realized the dispensation beyond description, by your essential mercy that is substantially found in you. You acted for mortal creation which was reduced to destruction. You did send the word, your son, our saviour Jesus Christ for its help. He completed everything for our salvation and taught us to pray and to offer you supplication. Hold us all worthy, O Lord, with unsullied lips, with the fervour of true faith and with openness befitting sons, may se shout towards you with one mouth, and pray and say: Our father in heaven.</p>
               <p>People: Hallowed be they name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer after the Lord's Prayer" corresp="#sachau-196-30">
               <p>Priest: O merciful father, do not loose hold of us so that we fall into temptations that we are unable to bear. But as a compassionate father, visit (us) the weak children. Do not deprive us of your grace. Do not hold back from us your gentle chastening. Do not turn your face from us. Do not cast from us your sheepfold, because yours is the splendor, glory and kingdom and of your only begotten son.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
               <p>Deacon: To the Lord our heads.</p>
               <p>People: In front of you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="The Third Benediction" corresp="#sachau-196-31">
               <p>Priest: O Lord, bless with your right hand carrying blessings this your believing people who with meekness of mind bend their necks before your mercy and await your overflowing gifts, so that from every filth and blemish of sin, we may be cleansed as we partake in the holy body and divine bloos of your Christ. We offer up all praises and exaltations and glories proper to the richness of your compassion and to your only begotten son and the Holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Prayer of Thanksgiving" corresp="#sachau-196-33">
               <p>Priest: Peace.</p>
               <p>People: With ...</p>
               <p>Priest: May ...</p>
               <p>Deacon: With fear.</p>
               <p>Priest: The holies ...</p>
               <p>People: One is the father.</p>
               <p>Priest: One is the holy father.</p>
               <p>Priest. Prayer after communion: We offer up due thanksgiving to you, O God. Continually, to the best of our power, we give thanks as we implore you, O our God, that these mysteries which we have received may be for us for the remission of debts and for the forgiveness of the sins. By the grace and mercy and philanthropy of your only begotten son with your Holy Spirit preserve and redeem us now.</p>
               <p>People: Amen.</p>
               <p>Deacon: For the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation-liturgical-section" n="Concluding Prayer" corresp="#sachau-196-34">
               <p>Priest: Before you, merciful Lord, we bow down our necks. Grant them, O benevolent Lord, the harmony of true love and right standing, showering on them by your mercy all abundant goodness and everlasting blessings. Preserve them from all afflictions, for you alone are the compassionate shepherd, who gave up himself and saved the lost souls. We offer up praise to you and to your father who answers supplications, and to your Holy Spirit, the giver of live to the creatures, now. (Completed)</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="literature" n="Literature" xml:lang="en">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Abbeloos, J.B. / Lamy, T.J.</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Gregorii Barhebraei. Chronicon Ecclesiasticum</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">1, Leuven: Peeters, 1872</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Baumstark, Anton</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Geschichte der syrischen Literatur</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Mit Ausschluß der christlich-palästinensischen Texte, Bonn: A. Marcus und E. Webers Verlag Dr. jur. Albert Ahn, 1922, 248-256: Jakob von Edessa</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Chabot, J.-B.</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Chronique de Michel le Syrien</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Patriarche Jacobite D'Antioche (1166-1199). Éditée pour la première fois et traduite en francais par J.-B. Chabot. Tome II, Paris: Ernest Leroux, 1901</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Chabot, J.-B.</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Chronique de Michel le Syrien</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Patriarche Jacobite D'Antioche (1166-1199). Éditée pour la première fois et traduite en francais par J.-B. Chabot. Tome IV. Texte syriaque, Paris: Ernest Leroux, 1910</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Drijvers, Hendrik J. W.</author>
                  <title>Jakob von Edessa (633 - 708)</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">XXX</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Theologische Realenzyklopädie</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">16, 2010</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>xxx-xxx</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Duval, Ruben</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Anciennes Littératures Chrétiennes. II. La Littérature Syriaque</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Bibliothèque de l'enseignement de l'histoire ecclésiastique, Paris: Librairie Victor Lecoffre, J. Gabalda, troisième edition 1907, 374-376: Jacques d'Edesse</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Ibrahim, Gregorios Yohanna / Kiraz, George Anton</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Studies on Jacob of Edessa</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 25, Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2010</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Ishac, Ephrem Aboud</author>
                  <title>Eschatology in Jacob of Edessa's Anaphora</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">Orthodox Diocese of Severin and Strehaia</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Orientalia Patristica</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Papers of the International Patristic Symposium. April 23 - 27 2018, Didahia Severin Publishing, fifth edition 2019</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>166-200</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Kruisheer, Dirk / van Rompay, Lucas</author>
                  <title>A Bibliographical Clavis to the Works of Jacob of Edessa</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute and Gorgias Press</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Hugoye</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Journal of Syriac Studies, Vol. 1.1</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>35-56</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Raes, Alphonsus</author>
                  <title>Anaphora Syriaca. XXI. Iacobi Edesseni</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">Raes, Alphonsus</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Anaphorae Syriacae</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Quotquot in Codicibus Adhuc Repertae Sunt. Cura Pontificii Instituti Studiorum Orientalium. Editae et Latine Versae. Vol. III - Fasc. 1, Roma: Pontificium Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1981</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>46-71</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Sachau, Eduard</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Verzeichniss der Syrischen Handschriften</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Die Handschriften-Verzeichnisse der Königlichen Bibliothek in Berlin. 23. Band, Berlin: A. Asher, 1899.</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Salvesen, Alison</author>
                  <title type="article">Jacob of Edessa's Life and Work: A Biographical Sketch</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">ter Haar Romeny, Bas</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Jacob of Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His Day</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Monographs of the Peshitta Institute Leiden. Studies in the Syriac Versions of the Bible and their Cultural Contexts 18, Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2008</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>1-10</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Salvesen, Alison G.</author>
                  <title type="article">Yaʿqub of Edessa</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">Kiraz, George Anton</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Electronic Edition</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange><ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/entry/Yaqub-of-Edessa"/> (last visited, 16.06.2024)</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author rend="editor">ter Haar Romeny, Bas</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">Jacob of Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His Day</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Monographs of the Peshitta Institute Leiden. Studies in the Syriac Versions of the Bible and their Cultural Contexts 18, Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2008</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Tilly, Michael</author>
                  <title type="article">Jakob von Edessa</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">XXX</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Biographisch-bibliographisches Kirchenlexikon</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">2. xxx: xxx, 1990</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>1461-1463</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Tubach, J.</author>
                  <title type="article">Jakob von Edessa</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">XXX</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">4. Tübingen et al: Mohr Siebeck et al., 2008</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>xxx-xxx</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>van Ginkel, Jan J.</author>
                  <title>Jakob von Edessa in der Chronographie des Michael Syrus</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="single">Tamcke, Martin</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Syriaca. Zur Geschichte, Theologie, Liturgie und Gegenwartslage der syrischen Kirchen</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">2. Deutsches Syrologen-Symposium (Juli 2000, Wittenberg). Studien zur Orientalischen Kirchengeschichte 17, Hamburg: LIT, 2002</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>115-124</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Varghese, Baby</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">West Syrian Anaphoras</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">Awsār Slāwōt’ō 4, Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute, 2017, 132-147: Anaphora of Jacob of Edessa</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="article" rend="space-after">
                  <author>Watt, John W.</author>
                  <title type="article">Jakob von Edessa</title>
                  <bibl>
                     <editor rend="multiple">Riedweg, Christoph; Horn, Christoph; Wyrwa, Dietmar</editor>
                     <title type="book" subtype="main">Grundriss der Geschichte der Philosophie. Die Philosophie der Antike. 5.3. Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</title>
                     <title type="book" subtype="addition">Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018</title>
                  </bibl>
                  <citedRange>2474-2478</citedRange>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="book">
                  <author>Wright, William</author>
                  <title type="book" subtype="main">A Short History of Syriac Literature</title>
                  <title type="book" subtype="addition">London: Adam and Charles Black, 1894, 141-154: Jacob of Edessa</title>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
         <div type="weblinks" n="Weblinks" xml:lang="en">
            <p rend="space-after">The pictures of manuscript Sachau 196 are available online via the Staatsbibliothek Berlin: <ref target="http://resolver.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/SBB000055A900000007"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Abbeloos / Lamy 1872: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/BarHebraeusChroniconEcclesiasticumVol.1/mode/2up"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Chabot 1901: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/MichelLeSyrien2"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Chabot 1910: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/ChroniqueDeMichelLeSyrienTome4/mode/2up"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Duval 1907: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/LaLittratureSyriaque"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Nr. 151 (Sachau 185. 196. 152.) in the catalogue of Sachau 1899: Available online via the Staatsbibliothek Berlin: <ref target="http://resolver.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/SBB0000720B00160037"/></p>
            <p rend="space-after">Wright 1894: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/shorthsy00wrig/mode/2up"/></p>
            <p>Baumstark 1922: Available online via Internet Archive: <ref target="https://archive.org/details/geschichtedersyr00baumuoft"/></p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI> 